Victor Prokhorov

♦ https://victorprokhorov.github.io | ✓ victorprokhorov91@gmail.com | (+44)07818927970

SKILLS

Programming Python, PyTorch (see: pps-vae), TensorFlow (see: hsvae, kl-text-vae,

text2path)

Research Communication communicated my research via publications at: ICML, AAAI, NAACL,

EMNLP; communicated research for public audiences of peers: poster presentation at Microsoft Research Cambridge, UK, 2020 and poster presentation at Caparle NLP Supersit. Zwick Switzerland, 2010.

sentation at Google NLP Summit, Zurich, Switzerland, 2019.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Postdoctoral Researcher, University of Edinburgh, ExLab

Apr 2022 - Apr 2024

- conducted a research on deep generative models with interpretable latent representations see project
 [tl;dr: the objective is to build an interpretable latent variable model for visual and language modalities
 by grounding the latent representation in the images
- was responsible for leading of the project (e.g., defining current priorities, managing work with an external collaborator), a mathematical formulation of a variational autoencoder model, its implementation [code] and communicating the findings via a publication [paper]

Research Intern, Montreal Institute for Learning Algorithms (MILA)

Sep 2020 - Dec 2020

- conducted a research on deep generative models with symbolic latent representations for text [tl;dr: instead of pretraining a model to learn distributed representation of text which has been proven useful in transfer learning setup, in the project we aimed to induce reusable, graph-based symbolic representation of text]
- was responsible for a mathematical formulation of a variational autoencoder model and its implementation

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

- 1. Victor Prokhorov and Ivan Titov and Siddharth N, Autoencoding Conditional Neural Processes for Representation Learning in ICML 2024 [code] [tl;dr: develops the Partial Pixel Space Variational Autoencoder that casts Conditional Neural Process (CNP) context as latent variables learnt simultaneously with the CNP] [keywords: generative models; variational autoencoders; conditional neural processes; representation learning; interpretability; vision]
- 2. Mattia Opper and **Victor Prokhorov** and Siddharth N, StrAE: Autoencoding for Pre-Trained Embeddings using Explicit Structure in EMNLP 2023 (main) [tl;dr: investigates how explicit structure affects embedding quality] [keywords: autoencoders; representation learning; interpretability; structure induction; NLP]
- 3. Victor Prokhorov and Yingzhen Li and Ehsan Shareghi and Nigel Collier, Learning Sparse Sentence Encoding without Supervision: An Exploration of Sparsity in Variational Autoencoders in RepL4NLP 2021 (workshop) [code] [tl;dr: presents a novel VAE model with sparse latent representations for text representation and generation] [keywords: generative models; variational autoencoders; sparsity; representation learning; interpretability; NLP]
- 4. Lan Zhang and Victor Prokhorov and Ehsan Shareghi, Unsupervised Representation Disentanglement of Text: An Evaluation on Synthetic Datasets in RepL4NLP 2021 (workshop) [code] [tl;dr: uses the existing disentanglement VAE models to study the challenges of disentanglement for text] [keywords: generative models; variational autoencoder; disentanglement; representation learning; NLP]

- 5. Victor Prokhorov and Ehsan Shareghi and Yingzhen Li and Mohammad Taher Pilehvar and Nigel Collier, On the Importance of the Kullback-Leibler Divergence Term in Variational Autoencoders for Text Generation in WNGT 2019 (workshop) [code] [tl;dr: uses an information-theoretic framework to study an effect of the rate and distortion on text generation] [keywords: generative models; variational autoencoder; representation learning; model analysis; information theory; NLP]
- 6. **Victor Prokhorov**, Mohammad Taher Pilehvar, Dimitri Kartsaklis, Pietro Lio, Nigel Collier, Unseen Word Representation by Aligning Heterogeneous Lexical Semantic Space in **AAAI 2019** [tl;dr: uses knowledge graphs to learn representations for rare and out-of-vocabulary words] [keywords: representation learning; knowledge graphs; NLP]
- 7. **Victor Prokhorov**, Mohammad Taher Pilehvar, Nigel Collier, Generating knowledge graph paths from textual definitions using sequence-to-sequence models in **NAACL 2019** [code] [tl;dr: sequence-to-sequence model that grounds sentence meaning in a knowledge graph] [keywords: representation learning; interpretability; knowledge graphs; NLP]

EDUCATION

2017 - 2022 PhD in Computation, Cognition and Language at University of Cambridge

 Ph.D. Thesis: Injecting Inductive Biases into Distributed Representations of Text, under supervision of Nigel Collier and Ehsan Shareghi

2016 - 2017 MPhil in Advanced Computer Science at **University of Cambridge** (Distinction) 2013 - 2016 BEng in Computer Science and Electronics at **University of Bristol** (First Class)

Honors & Awards

- Mitacs Globalink Research (Mitacs, **Awarded**; the award required in person presence in Canada; due to COVID outbreak did not accept)
- Student Travel Grant (Workshop: Neural Generation and Translation)

ACTIVITIES

- Co-organiser for Edinburgh NLP Meetings, 2022-2023
- Co-organiser for Dagstuhl ELLIS NLP Workshop, 2022
- Reviewer for ICLR, 2022 and ACL ARR, 2021

Last updated: May 14, 2024